ARAF RAHMAN

(347) 583-5253 | araf.rahmn@gmail.com | LinkedIn: arafrahman | github: araf-rahman

Lead QA Engineer

Known as a go to resource possessing a strong background in full stack web development and extensive experience in QA testing for web-based applications. Excels in data analysis and technology management and can effectively communicate complex technical concepts to both technical and non-technical stakeholders. Proficiency in QA software testing and automation tools, coupled with the ability to design and manage test plans, ensures efficient bug detection and faster testing times. With strong leadership skills and a versatile technical skill set, they are well-suited to excel.

SKILLS

QA Software Testing/Automation | Selenium/Cypress/Puppeteer | JIRA/Pivotal Tracker/Intercom | Rails-Ruby Framework | Rack/ Sinatra | CSS/SCSS | JavaScript/ Angular/React/ Redux/Jest | Node.js | Postgres/SQL/Snowflake/ Elasticsearch | Redshift/Airflow. | MongoDB | New Relic | Rollbar | Heroku/AWS | CI/CD/CircleCi/Jenkins | PeopleSoft 9.2 | Computer Science |

Bilingual: Bengali, Hindi

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

BrainPOP New York, NY

Jan 2024 - Present

QA Engineer – Report Squad Lead

Lead the Report Squad QA Initiative and meticulously execute functional and integration test cases, ensuring they're completed within specified timeframes and test environments, using the right data for accuracy. By harnessing the Selenium framework in Java, automate tests to streamline procedures, enhancing efficiency across projects

- Execute functional and integration test cases meticulously within specified timeframes, test environments, and utilizing appropriate test data.
- Utilize Selenium framework written in Java to automate tests, ensuring efficiency and accuracy in testing procedures.
- Perform API testing, My SQL database testing, and data warehouse testing to validate complex datasets and ensure data integrity.
- Develop comprehensive test plans, test cases, test scripts, and test reports for multiple projects of varying scope and complexity.
- Proactively report and document defects and bugs, including assessing their priority and severity, and effectively close resolved issues.
- Provide valuable estimates and feedback to project managers for scheduling purposes, contributing to efficient project management.
- Maintain a proficient understanding of BrainPOP's administrative systems, products, and services, ensuring thorough testing coverage across website and app functionalities.

NEW VISIONS FOR PUBLIC SCHOOLS, New York, NY QA Lead

October 2017 - August 2023

Collaborated responsively across teams with engineers, data analysts, designers, product managers, and school support staff, facilitating cross-team communication and using knowledge of code base to efficiently resolve technical issues.

Performed QA Lead role daily/during supervisor absences, delegating responsibilities to team members to
maintain release schedule and produce a polished, user-friendly product with a high impact on student equity
across the largest school district in the US.

- Designed and managed implementation of Automated/Smoke test plan for entire application, resulting in 35% increase in bugs caught before reaching production.
- Organized testing automation feasibility analysis-built proof of concept, and lead development and testing of automation framework from scratch using Selenium/Cypress/Puppeteer, reducing testing times by 53%
- Managed code deployment process from various staging environments to production, including prioritizing features and fixes by user impact, while maintaining a rapid continuous-release cycle of development of 40– 76 JIRA cards per sprint.

NYC HEALTH +HOSPITALS, New York, NY Data Analyst

February 2017 - November 2017

Analyzed and reported trends throughout the entire health system and provided real-time data dashboards for HR leadership.

- Processed and analyzed Leave Administration Department reports, improving employee performance, and reducing operations budget.
- Made recommendations based on data to improve the operations of various departments to ensure NYC
 Health + Hospital's strategic goals were met accordingly.
- Presented the significance of data to department leads and provided training.
- Attended strategic meetings as required with Environment of Care, Workplace Violence, etc.
- Improved workflow through developing resources such as scheduling software and organizing communication between staffing leaders.

Assisting Coordinating Manager,

March 2015 - January 2017

- Improved employee relations by guiding employees through FMLA, benefits, retirement, and other relevant processes.
- Conducted absence and leave management training for managers, supervisors, and new employee orientation.
- Handled benefits, LOA inquiries, and complaints to ensure a quick and equitable resolution.

Data Specialist, HR Training & Development,

February 2014 - March 2015

- Responsible for departmental reporting, data integrity, and accuracy of HR systems.
- Reviewed hospital's human resources requirements & guidelines to ensure legal compliance.
- Managed a team of 9 people in entry of training data into PeopleSoft ELM and HRIS.

EDUCATION

Bachelor in Computer Science (B.S.)

Lehman College

QA Software Testing Training
Per Scholas